ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



50, BC Das Lane, Lalbagh, Dhaka, BD



+88-01943753798

arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

A machine learning researcher expert in applying deep learning & cloud computing in computer vision, data-driven modern astronomy and practical robotics & systems engineering application in order to serve the society & in greater sense the world, and encourage collaborative endeavor to explore outer world for better future of mankind.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering

Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science GPA: 5.00/5.00

Jul 2012 - Aug 2014

Class Position: 1st/60

Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science GPA: 5.00/5.00

Jan 2010 - May 2012

Class Position: 1st/60

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant & Software Team Advisor

Model & Project Lab, Int. Mars Rover Competition (URC & ERC) Sep 2019 – Present Supervisors: Dr. Md. Ashigur Rahman and Mizanul H. Chowdhury Dhaka, Bangladesh Topic: Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM, AR Tag and Object Detection for Safe Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.

Researcher & Collaborator

Undergraduate Thesis

Mar 2018 - Apr 2019

Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur and Dr. Muhammad Abir

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project

Mar 2017 - Feb 2018

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

Researcher & Technical Lead

Microsoft BD Internship Project

Feb 2017 - May 2017

Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project

Jul 2016 - Feb 2017

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for

Blind People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team Instructor at Model & Project Lab, BUET

• National Space Carnival & Camp Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps

• Bangladesh Astronomical Society Instructor for Workshops & Seminars Sep 2019 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Jun 2019 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan 2016 - May 2019 Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization) Jun 2019 – Present Head of STEM Education & Development Dhaka, Bangladesh Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education Specially among Children and Women of Bangladesh.

• American Astronomical Society

Country Co-Ordinator & Member

Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh in accordance with AAS, and Reported to Proper Authority for Publishing on their Monthly Magazines.

• Bangladesh Astronomical Society
Organizer & Member
Activities: Instructed and Organized Workshops, Quizzes and Seminars on Space and Astronomy to Promote Space Education among Future Generation of Bangladesh.

PUBLICATIONS

- **A. Chatterjee**, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," *2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI)*, Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- **A. Chatterjee**, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," *Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS)*, Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

Microsoft Bangladesh
 Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products

 Khulna Power Company Limited
 Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)

 Feb 2017 - May 2017
 Dhaka, Bangladesh
 Oct 2018 - Oct 2018
 Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- **Prg. Language:** Python, C++, C#, C, Arduino, JavaScript, HTML, PHP, CSS, SQL & LATeX.
- **Framework & OS:** ROS, Nvidia Isaac Sdk, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, WordPress, Linux, Mac & Windows.
- **Software & Tool:** Git & GitHub, Bash, Docker, MySQL, MIPAR, SOLIDWORKS, AutoCAD, Ansys, Eagle, PLC, Blender3D, Unity & Unreal Engine 4 & Microsoft Office Family.
- IDE, Compiler & Text Editor: CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Node.js, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Spyder, Visual Studio Code, Notepad++ & Sublime Text.

- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, RoboMaker & Storage, Google Cloud Platform & Colab & Microsoft Azure Cloud Platform.
- **Hardware:** GPS, LIDAR, 3D Stereo Camera, Nvidia Jetson ARM Boards, Raspberry PI, Arduino Series & Nvidia AMD Boards with GTX & RTX Graphics.
- **Technology:** Computer Vision, SLAM & Path Planning, PCB Design, 3D Printing, AR & VR, Game Development, Web Development, GPU & Cloud Computing & Data Science.
- Language: Bangla, English & Hindi.
- Others: Astronomy, Creative Arts, Singing, Harmonium & Guitar Playing, Organizing, Show Hosting, Volunteering, Swimming, Cycling, Playing Cricket, Football & Badminton.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

• 2nd in Asia and 16th across the Globe in European Rover Challenge	Sep 2019
European Space Foundation (ESF) & European Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, PL
Hon. Mention in National Project Show Competition	Jul 2017
IEEE SS12 & Maker Fair, UIU	Dhaka, BD
• 1st in National Project Show Competition	Jun 2017
EEE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 3 rd in Inter University Project Show Competition	May 2017
Mechanical Festival, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1st in National Poster Presentation Competition	Mar 2017
Robolution, MIST	Dhaka, BD
• 2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition	Dec 2016
CSE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
 Gold, Bronze & Silver Recipient of Duke of Edinburgh Int. Award 	Dec 2019
Duke of Edinburgh International Award Association	London, UK
• 1st in All Classes in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2002-2014
Elizabeth Primary Sc., Khulna BKS Sc., Khulna Pub. Cl.	Khulna, BD
• Govt. Board Scholarship in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2006-2014
Education Board of Bangladesh Govt., Jessore	Khulna, BD
Olympiad Achievements:	
• 1st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14 • 1st in Reg. R. of Zoology	Olympiad'14
• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13 • 3 rd in Reg. R. of Math O	lympiad'14

CERTIFICATIONS

- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- Wireless Communications for Everybody by Yonsei University on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **AstroTech:** The Science and Technology behind Astronomical Discovery by The University of Edinburgh on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **Image and Video Processing:** From Mars to Hollywood with a Stop at the Hospital by Duke University on Coursera, Oct 2019.
- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 Course) by Deeplearning.ai on Coursera, Sept 2018.
- A Short Course on **Nuclear Power Engineering** by Institute of Nuclear Power Engineering, BUET, Apr 2018.

LEADERSHIPS

•	Head of STEM Education & Development	Youthprenuer Network
•	Software Team Lead	Team Interplanetar, BUET
•	Technical Lead of Internship Project	Microsoft BD
•	President (Senior Rover Mate)	BUET Rover Scout Group

President

- Team Lead for Development & Planning
- Founding Member
- Country Co-Ordinator
- **Organizing** Secretary

Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET
ESAB, BUET Unit
Sceptre
American Astronomical Society
Nuclear Engineering Club, BUET

VOLUNTEERING

• Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)

Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people.

• BUET Rover Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on annual sports day, alumni day & admission test day at BUET.

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on medical camps, tree plantation events & sports day at KBKSS.

WORKSHOPS & SEMINARS

- National Leadership Conference-2019 arranged by WOC and English Olympiad.
- Youth Leadership Summit-2016 organized by Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre.
- 4th BIRDS International Workshop on **Demystifying Satellites** org. by BRAC University.
- Seminar on "Zero Robotics" organized by Dept. of Mechanical Engineering, BUET.
- Introducing Bangladesh Model World Health Organization & Workshop on WHO Simulation organized by BMWHO & UNYSAB.
- Authorship Workshop on How to Publish a Technical Paper with IEEE org. by IEEE.
- Training on **AI for Beginners** organized by Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET.
- Workshops on **CFD**, **Ansys Fluent**, **Solidworks & 3D Printing** org. by Involute Tech BD.
- Workshops on **PCB & Graphic Designing** organized by IEEE, BUET & BD Section.
- Workshop on **Overall Understanding of Scouting** org. by BUET Rover Scout Group.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
- American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME)
- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- American Physical Society (APS)
- American Nuclear Society (ANS)
- Bangladesh Astronomical Society (BAS)
- Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre Graduate Network (BGN)
- Engineering Students Association of Bangladesh (ESAB)

REFERENCES

Dr. M. A. Rashid Sarkar

Academic Advisor Ex. Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Professor, Dept. of Nuclear Eng., MIST. Email: rashid@me.buet.ac.bd

• Dr. Maglub Al Nur

Thesis Supervisor Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Email: maglub@me.buet.ac.bd

Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor Ex. Post Doc. R. Associate, Dept. of NSE, MIT. Imaging Specialist, Phoenix Nuclear Labs. Email: miabir@mit.edu

Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Project Co-Supervisor Arch. & Admin of ZR, Space Sys. Labs, MIT. Email: mizanul@mit.edu